# Leonard Kiefer, Ph.D.

#### **Economist**

124 South Spring Street, Falls Church, VA 22046 • (614) 209-1550 • lenkiefer@hotmail.com

# **Summary**

I help people understand the economy, housing and mortgage markets with expert analysis.

### Skills

#### **Economics/Statistics**

Extensive experience working with large data, e.g. HMDA, Loan Level Mortgage Performance Data (millions of records over many years), public government data (ACS, AHS), and forecasting databases.

Deep knowledge of advanced forecasting techniques and industry models (e.g. Macroadvisers' MA/US model).

Active researcher on housing and mortgage markets with recent papers on <u>mortgage underwriting</u>, <u>REO flows</u>, and <u>homeowners' transition into/out of negative equity</u>.

### **Programming**

Advanced: SAS, Matlab, R, Excel, Powerpoint, Tableau

Proficient: SPlus, Stata, Eviews

**Beginner:** Python, Javascript (D3.js and related packages for interactive data visualization)

#### **Communications**

**Spoken:** Excellent oral presentation skills with frequent presentations to audiences large and small, technical specialists, mortgage industry professionals, and general audiences. In 2014 I spoke at over 20 private/public events to a combined audience of over 2,000. Experience with radio/television live/taped interviews.

Writing: Numerous research papers and articles, including monthly forecast outlooks and quarterly reports.

For Samples See: <a href="http://www.freddiemac.com/finance/ehforecast\_archives.html">http://www.freddiemac.com/finance/ehforecast\_archives.html</a>

Data Visualization: Experience wrangling data and presenting in innovative ways.

For Samples See: http://public.tableausoftware.com/profile/leonard.kiefer#!/

### Leadership

Over four years of management experience, excellent record of cross-division collaboration.

# **Experience**

Deputy Chief Economist • Freddie Mac • McLean, VA

December 2012-Present

Senior Economist • Freddie Mac • McLean, VA

October 2009-December 2012

Assistant Professor • Texas Tech University • Lubbock, TX

August 2007-June 2008

## **Education**

2007

M.A. • Economics • The Ohio State University • Columbus, OH

2003

B.A. • Economics • University of Kentucky • Lexington, KY

2002